<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter id="About_UpWatch">
    <title>About UpWatch</title>
    <sect1 id="Upwatch_History">
    <title>History</title>
    <para>UpWatch is born from the loins of Netland Internet Services BV, Amsterdam, 
    The Netherlands. We are a hosting company which started in 1993 (when even Bill Gates knew
    nothing of the internet). We started doing managed hosting in 1995, and that's when
    we found out about monitoring. The hard way.</para>
    <para>It became clear that customers can easily bring down their own server on impossible
    moments, and that it doesn't look very good if you both find out about that the monday 
    after. So we started doing SLA's and limit customer rights on their own server.</para>
    <para>Initially we used Big Brother (bb4.com) for monitoring. This is an outstanding
    and useful package, and we have been using it for many years. But it has a few downsides.
    One is scalability. It does not scale well to hundreds of hosts. Also it has a
    geek-like look, we felt we couldn't give the URL to our customers. Third problem
    was integration with our backoffice.</para>
    <para>At the same time yours truly was thinking about setting up a commercial
    service for monitoring servers remotely. All this culminated into UpWatch. So lets get 
    straight to the ..</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Upwatch_features">
    <title>Features</title>
    <para>This is the full list of relevant upwatch features:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>OS support: clients available for Linux, Windows, FreeBSD, Solaris</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>GUI is multi-language enabled (uses gettext)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>GUI has mobile client support</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>GUI is brandable, you can give it your own look &amp; feel</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Generates realtime graphs from the database</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Notifications by email or SMS.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Clients for: HTTP GET, IMAP, MSSQL, MySQL, PING, POP3, PostgreSQL, SMTP, 
    SNMP GET, TCP connect (any port)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Local client detects: CPU load, loadavg, swap use, I/O use, memory use, and
    where supported hardware info like CPU temperature, fan speed and Power voltages. Also you can
    set it up to scan any logfile using regular expressions you supply.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Scalable: designed for monitoring tens of thousands of hosts</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Multi-tenanting: multiple companies can run monitoring services for network
    of multiple client-companies using the same backend+probe serverpark</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Extensive and complete documentation, partly generated from source</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Secure: run as ordinary user, developed with security in mind</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Fully opensource: GUI built on Apache/PHP, Backend on C/Perl, 
    Database is MySQL. Uses GNU configure.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>SuSE, RedHat and Fedora RPM's generated from sourcetree for easy installation</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
