<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter id="Configuration">
    <title>Configuration</title>
    <sect1 id="Probe_configuration">
       <title>Probe configuration</title>
       <para>First: it is extremely important your host clock is set correctly,
       and please use NTP to keep it up-to-date. If you don't, you will see very strange
       things happening, and what's more, if this gets into the database, it will
       be impossible to correct (apart from deleting all results alltogether).</para>
       <para>
          Each probe first reads the general configuration file <filename>/etc/upwatch.conf</filename>
          and then its own configurationfile in <filename>/etc/upwatch.d</filename> if it exists.
          Normally some general things like the debug and logging level, and the database access
          are specified in the first file, and any probe-specific setting in the second file. You can also
          override settings from the generic file in the probe-specific file.
       </para>
       <para> Each program has a manual page that documents options. Every long commandine option
          can also be entered in a configuration file.
       </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Database_configuration">
       <title>Database configuration</title>
        <para> First things first. Depending on the size of your installation you may
           run out of database or record space. It happened to me on the iptraf probe.
           I was measuring traffic for 4000 IP addresses and ran out of space after a month
           on the pr_iptraf_raw table - it hit the max_data_length limit. 
           I had to issue the following commands:
        <literallayout>
           $ mysql -u root --password=PASSWORD
           mysql> alter table pr_iptraf_raw max_rows = 1000000000;
        </literallayout>
           and this took almost two hours! So you better look at your own situation and
           adjust the settings MAX_ROWS and AVG_RECORD_SIZE accordingly for each table.
        </para>
   </sect1>
</chapter>

