<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter>
    <title>Installation</title>
    <sect1 id="Getting_upwatch">
        <title>Getting upwatch</title>
        <para> Currently, upwatch is not released, and is not allowed to be distributed. The
          only way to get it, is through written permission of UpWatch BV.</para>
        <para> If you aquired that, you will either receive access to CVS, or will receive a
            tar.gz file, or .RPM's.</para>
	 <para>Building and installing upwatch is not for the faint of heart. It uses lots of external
          libraries which may or may not be available on your platform. I myself use Redhat 8/9
          for development, and test compilation on RH7, Fedora Core 1/2, SuSE8.2, Solaris, 
          FreeBSD, and Yellowdog Linux 3.0.
       </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Requirements">
        <title>Requirements</title>
        <sect2 id="Run-time_requirements">
            <title>Run-time requirements</title>
            <para>First ensure that the time/date on all hosts is correctly set. </para>
            <para>Run time requirements differ per probe. Look in the corresponding .def file
                (or in the spec file for the probe), here's a list of everything we expect on a
                machine running all probes, and the database (I'll also list the version we use ourselves):</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>glib2 >= 2.0.4</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>xml2 (any version will do)</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>freetds >= 0.6.0 compiled with --enable-threadsafe</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>mysql 3.23.49</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>postgreSQL 7.1.0</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>net-snmp 5.0.6</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>-lcrypto</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>libpcap 0.6.2</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>libpcre 3.9.10</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>libncurses 5.2</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>libesmtp 1.0.1</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>libreadline 4.3</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Delivered with upwatch are libstatgrab (0.7), xmbmon 2.03, and the State Threads Library (1,4).</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="Build_requirements">
            <title>Build requirements</title>
            <para>You probably don't want to build upwatch yourself. Most likely you'll 
            grab the RPM packages and issue rpm -Uvh upwatch*rpm. Then skip to 
            <link linkend="Configuration">Configuration</link>.
            </para>
            <para> But on the other hand: you can build the software yourself. Apart from the normal GNU
                compilation tools, and the development versions of the above mentioned packages,
                you'll need the following on your system to build upwatch:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>autogen 5.3.6 (autogen.sourceforge.net)</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>if you also want to rebuild the manual: lynx 2.8.4, libxslt 1.0.15 and 
                docbook 1.48, including the entire toolchain: openjade, jadetex, tetex, 
                netpbm, perl-SGMLSpm.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>RPM tools, if you want to build RPM's</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>If you run RedHat, Debian or SuSE, don't forget to install the *-devel packages
                if there are any.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Compiling_upwatch">
        <title>Compiling upwatch</title>
        <para>Just in case you really want to (or need to) compile upwatch yourself, it's
           pretty easy:
        </para>
           <literallayout>
              $ tar xzvf upwatch-x.x.tar.gz
              $ cd upwatch-x.x
              $ ./configure
              $ make
           </literallayout>
        <para> Nothing to it... In case of problems, you're probably missing some library or
            header files, or they are in unexpected places. Look at the last parts
            of config.log.</para>
         <para>You can optionally specify --enable-monitors, --enable-iptraf --enable-server 
         or --enable-all to configure. Default configure only builds the client, docs, and utils.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Actual_Installation">
        <title>Actual Installation</title>
        <para> Before you install the software decide on the architecture. If you know in
            advance you'll have to monitor thousands of hosts, or the probes will exhaust your
            machine otherwise, you may have to split your installation across several machines.
            There may be more reasons to do that. Consult <link linkend="Scaling_up">Scaling
            up</link> and <link linkend="How_it_all_works">How it all works</link>
        </para>
        <para> For simplicity we assume you run everything on the same host. Type the following
           command as root:
        </para>
        <literallayout>
          $ make install
        </literallayout>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="php_pages">
       <title>PHP pages</title>
       <para> The PHP pages can just be copied to any directory. There is an include directory. Copy
          that a some location ouside the web root, and enter its location in the .htaccess file in the web root dir.
          Also enter the database details in config.php.
       </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Security_considerations">
       <title>Security considerations</title>
       <para> All upwatch directories are readable and writable by members of the group upwatch.
          Most all executables run as user upwatch.
          Some probes need root-access, most notable uw_ping, and they will be installed suid root.
          These probes drop root privileges wherever possible. Further you can assign each probe
          its own database user and grant that user access rights  to its own database tables.
          The probes itself don't write to the database, they only read from the
          <varname>pr_xxx_def</varname> tables.
       </para>
       <para> The PHP web user should have SELECT, UPDATE, DELETE access to all tables.
       </para>
       <para><command>uw_access</command>, and  <command>uw_accessbb</command> are
             the programs most vulnerable to crackers, as they wait
             for incoming connections on a TCP port (1985/1984). If possible, use <command>chroot</command> and
             firewall rules to limit connections to
             real probes only. Something similar holds for <command>mysql</command>. Most probes will want
             access, and passwords can be sniffed. For real security use ssh-tunnels.
       </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Database">
        <title>Database</title>
        <para>You actually need to create two databases, one for the probes to read from, and one 
        for the results to be written to. The first database should be called upwatch, the other
        one can be any name (we use netland). Create the databases as follows. (You DO have a root 
        password set for mysql don't you?)</para>
        <literallayout>
           $ mysqladmin -u root --password=PASSWORD create upwatch
           $ mysql -u root --password=PASSWORD upwatch &lt; upwatch-base.mysql
           $ mysqladmin -u root --password=PASSWORD create netland
           $ mysql -u root --password=PASSWORD netland &lt; upwatch-full.mysql
        </literallayout>
        <para>Of course you need to assign users and GRANT them access. We start with 
           the probes. Mosts probes need read access to their definition table. 
           In many situations you can use just one user for that. Give that user access with:
        </para>
        <literallayout>
           $ mysql -u root --PASSWORD=PASSWORD mysql
           mysql> GRANT SELECT ON upwatch.% TO probe@'192.168.1.23' IDENTIFIED BY 'PASSWD'
        </literallayout>
        <para>Do this for every host that runs probes.</para>
        <para>Next user is for the background processing and the php access:</para>
        <literallayout>
           $ mysql -u root --PASSWORD=PASSWORD mysql
           mysql> GRANT SELECT, INSERT, UPDATE, DELETE ON `netland`.* TO 'upwatch'@'localhost' IDENTIFIED BY 'PASSWD'
        </literallayout>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
