<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter>
    <title>Installation</title>
    <sect1 id="Getting_upwatch">
        <title>Getting upwatch</title>
        <para> Currently, upwatch is not released, and is not allowed to be distributed. The
            only way to get it, is through written permission of UpWatch BV.</para>
        <para> If you aquired that, you will either receive access to CVS, or will receive a
            tar.gz file, or .RPM's.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Requirements">
        <title>Requirements</title>
        <sect2 id="Run-time_requirements">
            <title>Run-time requirements</title>
            <para> Run time requirements differ per probe. Look in the corresponding .def file
                (or in the spec file for the probe, here's a list of everything we expect on a
                machine running all probes, and the database (I'll also list the version we use ourselves):</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>glib2 2.0.1</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>gnet 1.1.2</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>mysql 3.23.49</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>cURL 7.9.5</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>libnet 1.0.2a</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>libpcap 0.6.2</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="Build_requirements">
            <title>Build requirements</title>
            <para> Of course you can build the software yourself. Apart from the normal GNU
                compilation tools, and the aforementioned packages, you'll need the following on
                your system to build upwatch:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>autogen 5.3.6</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>libxslt 1.0.15</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>docbook 1.48</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>lynx 2.8.4</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>RPM tools, if you want to build RPM's</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>If you run redhat, debian or SuSe, don't forget to install the devel packages
                if there are any.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Compiling_upwatch">
        <title>Compiling upwatch</title>
        <para> Just in case you really want to (or need to) compile upwatch yourself, it's
           pretty easy:
        </para>
           <literallayout>
              $ tar xzvf upwatch-x.x.tar.gz
              $ cd upwatch-x.x
              $ ./configure
              $ make
           </literallayout>
        <para> Nothing to it... In case of problems, you're probably missing some library or
            header files, or they are in unexpected places. Look in config.log.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Actual_Installation">
        <title>Actual Installation</title>
        <para> Before you install the software decide on the architecture. If you know in
            advance you'll have to monitor thousands of hosts, or the probes will exhaust your
            machine otherwise, you may have to split your installation across several machines.
            There may be more reasons to do that. Consult <link linkend="Scaling_up">Scaling
            up</link> and <link linkend="How_it_all_works">How it all works</link>
        </para>
        <para> For simplicity we assume you run everything on the same host. In this case just
           install all rpm's on this host. What if you can't use RPM's? Then follow the following
           procedure as root:
        </para>
        <literallayout>
           $ mkdir /etc/upwatch.d
           $ cp config/upwatch.conf /etc
           $ for i in uw_*
           > do
           > cp $i/$i /usr/sbin
           > cp $i/$i.conf /etc/upwatch.d
           > done
           $ for i in uw_send uw_process uw_notify uw_traceroute
           > do
           > mkdir -p /var/spool/upwatch/$i/tmp
           > mkdir -p /var/spool/upwatch/$i/new
           > done
        </literallayout>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="php_pages">
       <title>PHP pages</title>
       <para> The PHP pages can just be copied to any directory. There is an include directory. Copy
          that a some location ouside the web root, and enter its location in the .htaccess file in the web root dir.
       </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Security_considerations">
       <title>Securiy considerations</title>
       <para> All of upwatch can be run as a non-root user, except the probes which need root-access,
          most notable, uw_ping. You can assign each probe its own user and grant that user access rights
          to its own database tables. The probes only read from the <varname>pr_xxx_def</varname> and
          the <varname>server</varname> tables.</para>
          <para> The PHP web user should have SELECT, UPDATE, DELETE access to all tables.
          </para>
          <para> <command>uw_access</command> is the program most vulnerable to crackers, as it waits
             for incoming connections on a TCP port (1985). If possible, use <command>chroot</command> and
             firewall rules to limit connections to
             real probes only. Something similar holds for <command>mysql</command>.Most probes will want
             access, and passwords can be sniffed. For real security use ssh-tunnels.
          </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Database">
        <title>Database</title>
        <para> Create the database as follows. We assume you have a root password set for mysql:</para>
        <literallayout>
           $ mysqladmin -u root --password=PASSWORD create upwatch
           $ mysql -u root --password=PASSWORD &lt; upwatch.mysql
        </literallayout>
        <para> Of course you need to assign users and GRANT them access. Note that mosts probes will
           want read access to their definition table and the server list. In many situations you can use just
           one user for that. Give that user access with:
        </para>
        <literallayout>
           $ mysql -u root --PASSWORD=PASSWORD mysql
           mysql> GRANT SELECT ON upwatch.pr_ping_def TO user@'192.168.170.23' IDENTIFIED BY 'PASSWD'
           mysql> GRANT SELECT ON upwatch.server TO user@'192.168.170.23' IDENTIFIED BY 'PASSWD'
        </literallayout>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
